Previously,
지난번에,
we talked about how Source Map works
소스 맵이 어떻게 작동하는지에 대해 알아봤죠.
Now,
이제,
it's time to explore how browsers use them
브라우저가 어떻게 소스 맵을 활용하여
to enhance your debugging experience
디버깅 경험을 향상시키는지 알아볼 차례입니다.
Let's go!
시작해 볼까요!
Source Maps are special
소스 맵은 특별합니다.
It only loads when you open DevTools
개발자 도구를 열 때만 로드되죠.
That makes a lot of sense,
이것은 매우 합리적입니다.
because it's better for performance
성능에 더 좋기 때문이고,
and your users don't need Source Maps
사용자들은 소스 맵을 필요로 하지 않으니까요.
To check which Source Maps are loaded,
어떤 소스 맵이 로드되었는지 확인하려면,
use the command-shift-P shortcut
command-shift-P 단축키를 사용하여
to open the Developer Resource tab
개발자 리소스 탭을 열고,
and refresh the page
페이지를 새로 고침 하세요.
The tab listed all the Source Maps
탭에 모든 소스 맵이 나열됩니다.
You can apply filters if the list goes too long
목록이 너무 길어지면 필터를 적용할 수 있습니다.
Great!
좋습니다!
Our project is built with HTML,
저희 프로젝트는 HTML,
TypeScript, and SCSS
TypeScript, 그리고 SCSS로 만들어졌습니다.
Let's see how DevTools can help us
개발자 도구가 어떻게 우리 코드를
pinpoint issues in our code
정확히 찾아내는지 한번 봅시다.
Click on the greeting button
반응 버튼을 클릭하세요.
In the console,
콘솔에서,
you can see that DevTools actually maps it to TypeScript
개발자 도구가 소스 맵 덕분에 실제로 TypeScript에 연결한 것을 볼 수 있습니다.
thanks to Source Maps
소스 맵 덕분이죠.
Click on the link
링크를 클릭해서
to open it in the Sources panel
소스 패널에서 열어보세요.
If you hover over the line at the bottom,
아래쪽의 선 위에 마우스를 올리면,
DevTools will reveal the exact location
개발자 도구가 정확한 위치를 보여줄 것입니다.
from which this file was mapped
이 파일이 매핑된 곳이죠.
Clicking on it will
클릭하면
take you directly to the generated file
생성된 파일로 바로 이동합니다.
DevTools automatically detects
개발자 도구는 자동으로
and formats your minified files
축소된 파일을 감지하고 포맷하여
for better readability
가독성을 높여줍니다.
You can undo the format by clicking
아래쪽 아이콘을 클릭하여
on the icon at the bottom
포맷을 취소할 수 있습니다.
Now,
이제,
what happens for minified files
소스 맵이 없는 축소된 파일은 어떻게 될까요?
without Source Maps?
개발자 도구에서
You can disable them
소스 맵을 비활성화하여
in DevTools to try it out.
확인해 볼 수 있습니다.
Open the three-dot menu,
세 개의 점 메뉴를 열고,
select Run command
명령 실행을 선택한 다음,
and enter Source Maps.
소스 맵을 입력하세요.
You have options
옵션이 있습니다.
to disable JavaScript
JavaScript를 비활성화하거나,
and CSS Source Maps.
CSS 소스 맵을 비활성화할 수 있습니다.
Let's disable the JavaScript Source Map
JavaScript 소스 맵을 비활성화하여
to see what happens.
어떻게 되는지 봅시다.
In the console,
콘솔에서,
the log location now
로그 위치가 이제
takes you to the compiled JavaScript file
소스 파일 대신 컴파일된 JavaScript 파일로 이동합니다.
instead of the source file.
소스 파일 대신 말이죠.
Imagine you want to change the logic of the random number.
랜덤 숫자의 로직을 변경하고 싶다고 상상해 보세요.
You will need to manually map the code
코드와 변수를 머릿속으로 수동으로 매핑해야 할 것입니다.
and variables in your mind.
머릿속에서 말이죠.
Let's re-enable the Source Map.
소스 맵을 다시 활성화해 봅시다.
Now,
이제,
try setting a breakpoint at the console.log.
console.log에 중단점을 설정해 보세요.
DevTools will automatically
개발자 도구가 자동으로
open the original file
원래 파일을 열고
and set the breakpoint there.
거기에 중단점을 설정합니다.
Pretty cool, right?
정말 멋지죠?
There are times where you have Source Maps,
소스 맵이 있지만,
but you want to keep it private,
특히 프로덕션 코드의 경우,
especially for your production code.
비공개로 유지하고 싶을 때가 있습니다.
In that case,
이 경우,
when you are debugging that,
디버깅할 때
you might want to attach
비공개 소스 맵을
the private Source Map manually.
수동으로 연결해야 할 수도 있습니다.
In this example,
이 예시에서는,
we hide the Source Map by default.
기본적으로 소스 맵을 숨겼습니다.
There is no source URL
생성된 코드에도 소스 URL이 없습니다.
in the generator code as well.
생성된 코드에도 말이죠.
Right-click on the page
페이지를 마우스 오른쪽 버튼으로 클릭하고
and select Add Source Map.
소스 맵 추가를 선택하세요.
Enter the URL
개인 소스 맵의
of your private Source Map.
URL을 입력하세요.
If the URL is invalid,
URL이 유효하지 않으면,
there will be warnings
개발자 리소스 탭과
in the Developer Resources tab
콘솔에 경고가 표시됩니다.
as well as the console.
콘솔에도 말이죠.
Try again with a valid URL.
유효한 URL로 다시 시도해 보세요.
And there you go.
자, 됐습니다.
The file is loaded successfully
파일이 성공적으로 로드되었고
and your source is once again mapped.
소스가 다시 한번 매핑되었습니다.
While Source Map is great,
소스 맵은 훌륭하지만,
there are some gotchas as well.
몇 가지 주의할 점도 있습니다.
Sometimes,
때로는,
the debugging might not work as expected
소스 맵 사양의 한계 때문에
due to the limitations of
디버깅이 예상대로 작동하지 않을 수 있습니다.
the Source Map specification.
소스 맵 사양의 한계 때문이죠.
Let's start a debugging session.
디버깅 세션을 시작해 봅시다.
When you hover over to the num variable,
num 변수 위로 마우스를 가져가면,
you can preview its value.
값을 미리 볼 수 있습니다.
In fact,
사실,
DevTools also supports inline preview.
개발자 도구는 인라인 미리 보기도 지원합니다.
And you can edit the value
그리고 스코프 창에서도
in the scope pane as well.
값을 편집할 수 있습니다.
Now,
이제,
you might be wondering,
변수 grid는 어떨지 궁금할 것입니다.
how about the variable grid?
변수 grid는 어떨까요?
Why is the line disabled
왜 이 줄은 비활성화되었고
and doesn't show any previews at all?
미리 보기가 전혀 표시되지 않을까요?
It is because your build tools are smart.
빌드 도구가 똑똑하기 때문입니다.
It detects that the grid variable can be removed
빌드 도구는 grid 변수를 제거하고
and embedded value straight away in the message.
값을 메시지에 바로 포함시킬 수 있음을 감지합니다.
Since the grid variable isn't mapped in the Source Map,
grid 변수가 소스 맵에 매핑되지 않았기 때문에,
DevTools won't be able to evaluate the value.
개발자 도구는 값을 평가할 수 없는 것입니다.
This usually happens for production code,
이는 보통 프로덕션 코드에서 발생하는데,
as the code is highly optimized.
코드가 고도로 최적화되어 있기 때문입니다.
Development builds tend to have a more relaxed configuration.
개발 빌드는 더 유연한 설정을 가지는 경향이 있습니다.
Another thing to keep in mind with Source Maps
소스 맵에서 염두에 두어야 할 또 다른 사항은
is that build tools may have slight variation
빌드 도구가 사양의 유연성 때문에
in how they handle the build
빌드를 처리하는 방식에
due to the flexibility in the spec.
약간의 차이가 있을 수 있다는 것입니다.
The flexibility allows customization
이 유연성은 맞춤 설정을 허용하고
and could lead to a more efficient build.
더 효율적인 빌드를 만들 수 있게 합니다.
However,
하지만,
the flexibility of the spec can lead to
사양의 유연성은 때때로
confusion at times as well.
혼란을 야기할 수도 있습니다.
For example,
예를 들어,
inspect the header.
헤더를 검사해 봅시다.
The CSS maps correctly to its original styles.scss.
CSS는 원래의 styles.scss에 제대로 매핑됩니다.
However,
하지만,
you might notice there are two CSS files
페이지 트리에서 CSS 파일이
in the page tree instead of just one.
하나가 아닌 두 개 있다는 것을 알 수 있습니다.
Look at your project folder.
프로젝트 폴더를 살펴보세요.
You are pretty sure there is only one CSS file with that name
그 이름의 CSS 파일은 하나밖에 없다는 것을 알고 있을 것입니다.
and the content is minified CSS.
그리고 그 내용은 축소된 CSS입니다.
What is happening here?
여기서 무슨 일이 일어나고 있는 걸까요?
Hmm...
음...
Is there a bug in DevTools?
개발자 도구에 버그가 있는 걸까요?
Well, not really.
글쎄요, 그렇지는 않습니다.
DevTools gets the information
개발자 도구는 소스 맵에서
from the Source Maps and displays them accordingly.
정보를 가져와서 그에 따라 표시합니다.
Open the Source Map.
소스 맵을 열어보세요.
It has two sources.
두 개의 소스가 있습니다.
DevTools generates the map files based on the list.
개발자 도구는 이 목록을 기반으로 맵 파일을 생성합니다.
Take note that those files mapped by DevTools have an italic name.
개발자 도구에 의해 매핑된 파일은 기울임꼴 이름으로 표시됩니다.
According to this line,
이 줄에 따르면,
DevTools maps and displays the unminified CSS.
개발자 도구는 축소되지 않은 CSS를 매핑하여 표시합니다.
Another CSS file without italic name
기울임꼴 이름이 없는 다른 CSS 파일은
is the actual minified CSS file on this.
실제 축소된 CSS 파일입니다.
Some build tools might just eliminate the intermediate level
일부 빌드 도구는 중간 단계를 생략하고
and map it straight from the minified CSS to SCSS.
축소된 CSS에서 SCSS로 바로 매핑할 수도 있습니다.
If that's the case,
그렇다면,
DevTools will only show you one CSS file
개발자 도구는 CSS 파일 하나만 표시할 것이고,
which might be closer to your expectation.
이는 여러분의 기대에 더 가까울 수 있습니다.
Well,
음,
the current Source Map spec
현재 소스 맵 사양은
doesn't actually detect how mapping should be done.
매핑을 어떻게 해야 하는지 실제로 감지하지 못합니다.
So,
그러니,
just take note of this
이 점을 알아두세요.
in case you have the same confusion next time.
다음에 같은 혼란을 겪지 않도록 말이죠.
Apart from that,
그 외에도,
you can turn on a setting in DevTools
개발자 도구에서 설정을 켜서
to view your original sources first
매핑된 경우 원래 소스를 먼저 볼 수 있습니다.
if they are mapped.
매핑된 경우에 말이죠.
By default,
기본적으로,
DevTools mixes and shows all files together.
개발자 도구는 모든 파일을 섞어서 함께 보여줍니다.
You can group them by altered and deployed.
변경됨과 배포됨으로 그룹화할 수 있습니다.
In this case,
이 경우,
the original files will show first in the altered section
변경됨 섹션에 원래 파일이 먼저 표시되고
and the compiled code shows in the deployed section.
배포됨 섹션에 컴파일된 코드가 표시됩니다.
By the way,
참고로,
DevTools uses a Source Map extension
개발자 도구는 스택 추적을 개선하기 위해
called x_google_ignoreList
x_Google_ignoreList라는 소스 맵 확장 프로그램을 사용합니다.
Follow this link to learn more.
자세한 내용은 이 링크(goo.gle/ignore-list)를 참조하세요.
I have a video explaining how it works as well.
작동 방식에 대한 설명 영상도 있습니다.
Alright,
좋습니다.
now you know everything about Source Map and DevTools.
이제 소스 맵과 개발자 도구에 대해 모두 알게 되었습니다.
If you have more questions,
궁금한 점이 있다면,
feel free to ask in the comments below.
아래 댓글에 자유롭게 질문해 주세요.
That's all.
이것으로 끝입니다.
See you in the next TechTool Tips.
다음 기술 도구 팁에서 만나요.
Ciao!
챠오!